[This episode celebrates the 40th anniversary
of Weekly Shonen JUMP.]
[Well, we feel it's somehow too good, so
we'll show the new opening a little later.]
[And so, the GinTama anime starts its third year!!]
I've cornered you. There is
nowhere for you to escape.
The game is over, uh-huh.
That's right. Give up peacefully, serial
bombers, Katsurayama, Josephine.
(銀時)｢ﾊｯﾊｯﾊ ｷﾞﾝﾀ｡
Ha ha ha. Ginta, you're the
one who's been cornered.
追い詰められたのは
お前のほうだ｣｡
I've already set bombs everywhere
in this building.
If Josephine pushes this switch,
everyone here will die.
What?!
I won't let you do it!
Domestic Violence!
There it is! Ginta-san's special weapon!
It's a very strong skill used to strike
a blow to the opponent's crotch!
With sixteen strikes a second,
his crotch is already damaged.
What?!
I-It doesn't work. Oh, I see. Oh my god!
｢あの服… あの服で
隠されているが➡
Those clothes... Those clothes make it tough
to see exactly where Josephine's crotch is.
ｼﾞｮｾﾌｨｰﾇの股間は
あそこじゃないんだ｣｡
It must be somewhere else.
Dokan.
｢ﾄﾞｶｰﾝ｣ …んだ ｵｲ！
Hey, wait.
まだ このﾏﾝｶﾞ 連載してたのかよ｡
いい加減 やめさせて➡
This manga is still being serialized?
Hey, JUMP. Stop it already and
let a rookie try something.
ｲｷのいい新人 入れろよ｡
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣よぉ…｡
なんだよ このﾏﾝｶﾞよぉ…
読みづらくてしゃ～ねえ｡
What's with this manga?!
It's so unreadable.
絵 汚ぇし
台詞 多すぎなんだよ ﾊﾞｶ野郎｡
The drawings are really rough, and
there's too much dialog, Idiot.
なにが ｢天地先生のﾏﾝｶﾞが
読めるのは 『少年ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ』だけ｣だよ｡
They say, "You can read Amachi
Sensei's manga only in JUMP."
[Note: "You can read XX Sensei's manga only in JUMP."
is a common line used in SHONEN JUMP magazine.]
読まされるのは ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣だけ！
の間違いだろうが！
That's wrong. "We're forced
to read it in JUMP."
そろそろ ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣もさ
『ﾜﾝﾊﾟｰｸ』とか 『BERUTO』を超える➡
I guess it's about time for JUMP to cultivate a
talent who can surpass "One Park" or "Belt."
[Note: One Park is a parody of One Piece. Belt is a parody of Naruto. Hanger Hanger is a parody of HUNTER x HUNTER which has a habit of taking long hiatuses.]
逸材を育てなきゃ
いけねえ時期だよ こりゃ｡
また戻ってきた
『ﾊﾝｶﾞｰ×ﾊﾝｶﾞｰ』だって➡
"Hanger Hanger" is back again, but we
won't know when it'll take off again.
次 また いつ休むか
わかんねえんだからよぉ｡
ｵﾚの勘だと 10年周期で そろそろ
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣に次の天才が来る頃だ｡
According to my instincts,
it's about time for the next genius to appear
in JUMP within the ten-year cycle.
(小西)詳しく意見を伺いたいねぇ｡
I'd like to hear more.
(小西)ｷﾐは 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』の
何が悪いというんだ｡
What's the problem with "Gintaman"?
I think it's fairly good. I like it.
結構 がんばってるじゃないか｡
好感が持てるよ｡
なんだ？ ﾎﾞｸ｡ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』のﾌｧﾝか？
ﾀﾞﾒだよ こんなﾏﾝｶﾞ 読んだら！
What's with you, kid?! Are
you a fan of Gintaman?
You shouldn't read this kind of
manga. It'll stunt your growth.
背が大きくならないぞ｡
ﾎﾞｸじゃない 小西だ｡
I'm not a kid, I'm Konishi.
『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』の何が悪いか
ﾎﾞｸは聞いてる｡
I'm asking you what the problem
is with Gintaman.
担当じゃねっ？
こんな状態になるまで➡
It's the editor's fault.
It's the fault of the editor in charge, who
has left the manga unattended until now.
放置してた担当編集が
悪いと思うね ｵﾚは｡
あ～あ… これだから素人は
ｲﾔになるなぁ…｡
That's how an amateur thinks.
担当が作家を
引っ張っていけるのも➡
The editor can only help lead the manga
author's manga into AKAMARU JUMP.
[Note: New SHONEN JUMP artist manga are often debuted in AKAMARU JUMP. If the manga becomes popular it is serialized in SHONEN JUMP.]
せいぜい赤ﾏﾙまでだよ｡
連載となると➡
Once it becomes a serialized manga, it's up to
the manga author to survive by vastly improving.
作家自身が成長せねば
生き残ることはできない｡
引っ張るまではいかんでも➡
Even if he can't lead the manga author,
暴走を止めることくらい
できるでしょ｡
he should at least be able to stop him
from going in the wrong direction.
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣のﾏﾝｶﾞは どっか
ぶっ飛んでるｴﾈﾙｷﾞｰが➡
I understand that the manga in JUMP
needs to have a lot of energy.
必要なのは わかるけど
行き過ぎた場合➡
But when the author goes too far,
手綱をとってやるのも
編集の役目だろ｡
it's the editor's responsibility to nudge
him in the right direction.
これ 絶対 ｵﾚが編集やった方が
いけるね｡ わかってねえよ ｺｲﾂ｡
Obviously, I should be the editor.
He doesn't know what he's doing.
どうせ ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣の編集なんて
高学歴だかなんだか➡
I bet the editors of JUMP are all highly educated
guys who've studied a lot of things,
知らねえけど 勉強しか
やってきてねえ➡
but don't understand the hearts of boys.
少年の心も
知らん野郎ばっかりなんだろ｡
[HAGA LAW OFFICE]
あ～ぁ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』さえなけりゃ
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣最高なんだけどな～！
Hah, it would be better if Gintaman
wasn't in JUMP.
＜小西:自分の仕事に
誇り 持ってますか？＞
[Gintaman Manuscripts]
Are you proud of your job?
[TEL]
はい もしもし お世話になります｡
Hello. Thanks for calling. This is Konishi
of JUMP's editorial department.
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣編集部 小西です｡
＜仕事… 楽しんでますか？
Are you enjoying your work?
仕事… 好きですか？＞
Do you like your job?
["The More Something Is Disliked,
The More Lovely It Is"]
[SHUEISHA]
(編集長)小西！
Konishi!
ﾃﾒｴ こんな下ﾈﾀ
使えるわけねえだろが～っ!!
Hey, you! There's no way I can approve
a dirty story idea like this!
うっ…｡
You can't jump into the gutter just because you
run out of decent ideas! That's not professional!
ﾈﾀに詰まったからって 下ﾈﾀで
ごまかそうとすんじゃねえ！
(編集長)あん？ ｺﾗ｡
なに 下ﾈﾀが売りですみたいな➡
What? Ah, ha! You're trying to use
smut to cover up a bad story, huh?
芸風のﾏﾝｶﾞにして そのへんの感じ
ごまかそうとしてんだぁ!?
ﾊﾞﾚﾊﾞﾚなんだよ 限界きてんのが…
底の浅さが!!
I can see you've reached
the limit of your abilities!
There's no depth at all! I'd be excited,
but for the wrong reason!
別の意味で ﾊﾗﾊﾗ ﾄﾞｷﾄﾞｷ
すんだろ～が!!
頼むよ ﾎﾝﾄ… 小西君よぉ…
ｲﾗｲﾗさせないでくれよ｡
Konishi-kun, please!
You're so aggravating!
これ以上 ｵﾚを
ﾊｹﾞちらかさないでくれよ！
My hair is falling out because of you!
ｾﾝﾀｰ分けって言い張るにも
限界があるぞ！ えっ おい!!
I can't tell people I part my hair in the
middle anymore! You hear me?!
見てみろ！ ﾃﾒｴと同期の吉沢を！
Look over there!
That's Yoshizawa, one of
your contemporaries!
(編集長)『Ｃｸﾚｲﾏﾝ』に 『ﾍﾟｽﾉｰﾄ』を
生み出した ｲｹﾒﾝ敏腕編集！
He's the good-looking, skillful editor-in-chief
who created "C.Clay-Man" and "Peth Note."
[Note: C.Clay-Man is a parody of D.Gray-Man.
Peth Note is a parody of Death Note.]
仕事も身長もﾁﾝｺも
お前の３倍はあるぞ！ おい！
Hey, his work, height and dick size are
all three times bigger than yours!
それに引き換え お前
なに それ!? なに あれ！
[Friendship, Diligence, Victory]
By contrast, look at you!
You're like a junior high student
both in height and work.
仕事も身長も中学生だろうが！
ﾁﾝｺにいたっては…➡
People like you usually have small...
お前 なんで ﾁﾝｺだけ ﾃﾞｹｴんだよ｡
You have a big pecker!
Even that makes me angry!
そういうところが
むかつくんだよ!!
いいか？ 次回の読者ｱﾝｹｰﾄが➡
Listen! If your next reader survey
comes up with the lowest score...
また 今回のような
最悪の結果であれば➡
小西… ﾃﾒｴも
担当ﾏﾝｶﾞ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』と一緒に➡
Konishi...
...you and your work
on "Gintaman" will...
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣から消えてもらう！
...no longer be needed for JUMP!
＜小西:なんで こんなことに
なってしまったんだろう…｡
Why have things changed so much?
なんで こんな目に遭わなきゃ
いけないんだろう…｡
Why do I have to languish like this?
もともと ﾎﾞｸが
集英社に入社したのは➡
The reason I joined Shueisha wasn't because
I wanted to help JUMP or anything like that.
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣が作りたかったとか
そういう理由からではなかった｡
『ﾒﾝｽﾞ ﾉﾝﾉ』編集部に入り
流行の発信基地になりたかった…｡
I just wanted to work in the MEN'S NON-NO editorial
department and write about today's fashion trends...
[Note: Men's Non-No is a fashion
magazine for men.]
最先端のｼﾃｨﾎﾞｰｲになり
ﾃﾞﾙﾓをはべらせ➡
I wanted to become a modern city boy
and be surrounded by models...
ｻﾞｷﾞﾝで ｼｰｽｰをたらふく ﾍﾞｰﾀｰして➡
...eat a lot of sushi in Ginza...
ｸﾗﾌﾞで毎晩 ﾕｰｺﾞｰしたかった…｡
...and party in nightclubs every night.
それが 何の因果か
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣編集部に配属され➡
I don't know why, but I was assigned
to JUMP's editorial department,
こんな ｲﾓくさいﾏﾝｶﾞの
制作に たずさわっている…｡
and I have to work on this
kind of shabby manga.
自分でも わからなかった
わかりたくもなかった…＞
I didn't understand it. I didn't
want to understand it.
おいおい… 今週も
まだ載ってるよ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』｡
Hey, hey. I still see "Gintaman"
in this week's issue.
Give me a break. It makes me sick.
いい加減にしてくれよ｡
不快なんだよ！
ﾏｼﾞ 編集 何考えてんだよ？
Really... I wonder what
the editor was thinking.
編集長 さっさと
作家と担当編集を処刑しろよな！
Editor-in-chief, hurry up and execute
the editor and the manga author.
これ以上 ｵﾚの｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣を
汚さないでくれ！
Please don't foul up my JUMP anymore.
I want to read more story-like comics.
もっと劇画っぽいのを読みたいよ｡
『ﾎﾜｲﾄﾃﾞﾋﾞﾙｽﾞ』とか 『ﾊﾞｯﾄｻｲﾀﾞｰ』とか｡
Like "White Devils" or "Bat Sider."
[Note: Parody of "Black Angels" and "God Sider".
Both were serialized in Shonen JUMP in the 80s. ]
じゃあ ﾃﾒｴが編集やれよ！
やれるもんなら やってみろよ！
Then you do the editing!!
Do it if you can!!
ｵﾚだってさ ﾎﾝﾄは
『ﾍﾟｽﾉｰﾄ』とか『Ｃｸﾚｲﾏﾝ』みてえな➡
In fact, I'd rather work on "Peth
Note" or "C.Clay-Man"!
ｵｼｬﾚで ｶｯｺｲｲのやりてえよ！
Something that's stylish and cool!
『ｸｲｯｸｼﾞｬﾊﾟﾝ』とか『ｽﾀｼﾞｵﾎﾞｲｽ』みてえな
ｻﾌﾞｶﾙ系の雑誌で特集 組まれて➡
I wish sub-culture magazines like "Quick Japan" or
"Studio Voice" would do special features about me.
[Note: Yoichi Shibuya is the CEO of Rockin' On and known for his long behind-the-scenes interviews with musicians and artists.]
I want to be interviewed about
behind-the-scenes news
制作裏話とか ３万字ｲﾝﾀﾋﾞｭｰとか
されてえよ 渋谷 陽一に！
and be the subject of one of Yoichi Shibuya's
30,000-character interviews.
でも… でもぉ！
But... But!
ｵﾚの担当は
『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』に『ﾒｿﾞﾝ･ﾄﾞ･ｷﾞﾝｷﾞﾝ』！
I have to be in charge of "Gintaman"
and "Maison de Gin-Gin"!
[Note: Maison de Gin-Gin is a parody
of Maison de Penguin in JUMP.]
なんで ｵﾚの担当 なんか
ｶｯｺ悪いのばっかりなんだよ～！
Why do I have to work
for uncool manga?!
ま… まぁまぁ 落ち着けよ！
Hey, hey, calm down.
ああ そっか… ｱﾝﾀが
やってたんだ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』の担当｡
Oh, I see... You're in charge
of "Gintaman."
いや あの あれだよ｡
Well, um, you know... I liked
"Maison de Gin-Gin."
『ﾒｿﾞﾝ･ﾄﾞ･ｷﾞﾝｷﾞﾝ』のほうは
ｵﾚ 結構 好きだったよ｡
(小西)うるせえよ 今さら！
もう ｱｲﾂ 実家 帰ったよ！
Shut up! It's too late! That guy already
went back to his parent's home.
帰って ｺﾝﾋﾞﾆで ﾚｼﾞ打ってるよ！
He went back and is working as a
cashier at a convenience store!
だ… 大丈夫だって！ ｱｲﾂなら
必ず帰ってくるって ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣に｡
D-Don't worry! He'll definitely return
to JUMP in a report manga.
[Note: Special report manga are
often only for the magazine.]
ﾚﾎﾟｰﾄﾏﾝｶﾞとかで！
(小西)ｺﾐｯｸｽに
ならねえじゃねえかよ！
Then it won't be a comic book anymore!
ﾎﾞｸは… この仕事に向いてない｡
...I'm inadequate for this job.
わかってる…
自分でだって わかってるさ｡
I know it... I've known it.
もともと あんまり
ﾏﾝｶﾞが好きじゃないんだ｡
In fact, I dislike manga in the first place.
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣は小さい頃から
読んでたけど➡
I've been reading JUMP
since I was a kid,
どちらかというと
友達と話を合わせるためだった｡
but it was just so I could talk about
the same subject with my friends.
ﾏﾝｶﾞを楽しいと思ったことがない｡
I never thought manga was fun.
そんなﾔﾂが 人を楽しませる
ﾏﾝｶﾞを作ることなんて➡
There's no way someone like me could
produce manga that people enjoy.
できるわけもない｡
ｸﾋﾞになって当然だ｡
It makes sense that I'd
get fired. That's right.
そうさ 最初から
ﾎﾞｸには向いてなかったんだ｡
I wasn't the right person for this
job from the very beginning.
ﾎﾞｸみたいなもんには
『ﾒﾝｽﾞ ﾉﾝﾉ』がお似合いだったんだ｡
Someone like me is just right
for MEN'S NON-NO.
せめて 『すばる』か
ぎりぎり 『Myojo』｡
Or at least "Subaru" or "Myojo."
JUMP is just out of the question.
[Note: Subaru is a literary magazine and Myojo is a magazine for popular boy bands and actors. Both published by Shueisha.]
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣は ﾑﾘだったんだ｡
｢月ｼﾞｬﾝ｣なら似合うんじゃねえか？
もう ねえよ｡
What about monthly JUMP?
It's already discontinued.
[Note: Monthly Shonen Jump
was discontinued in 2007.]
ｵﾚに やらせろよ！
Let me do it.
どうせ ｸﾋﾞなんだろ？
誰が編集やったって同じだろ｡
You'll get fired anyway, right? Then
it doesn't matter who the editor is.
ないなら作ればいい｡
If it doesn't exist, then just create it.
ﾃﾒｴがおもしろいと
思えるもんを考えるのが➡
It's your job to create something
that you think is fun, right?
ｱﾝﾀらの仕事だろ？
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣歴20年のｵﾚが➡
I've been reading JUMP for twenty years.
友情 努力 勝利の
何たるかを教えてやらぁ！
So I'll teach you about friendship,
diligence and victory.
Well...the author is very shy around people,
so please don't get all worked up.
あの… 人見知りの
激しい作家だから➡
あんま刺激しないようにね｡
打ち切りのことも言わないで｡
わかってるって！
And don't mention anything about this manga
possibly being discontinued, either.
I know.
ｱﾝｹｰﾄ結果とか 部数とか
原稿料とかも 絶対言わねえよ！
I definitely won't say anything about the reader survey
results, circulation or the manuscript fees.
言う気 満々にしか
聞こえないんだけど！
You sound like you'll talk all about it!
おはようございま～す！
Good morning.
なんだ おい 汚ねえ家だな！
掃除してんのかよ？
Man, this house is really dirty.
I wonder if he ever cleans up.
ああ ﾏﾝｶﾞ家なんて みんな
だいたい こんな感じだからね｡
Ah, most manga authors are like this.
一般人より 家にいる時間が多いし
片づける時間もないしね！
They stay at home more than the average
person and don't have time to clean up.
ﾏｼﾞかよ!? 普通に
らせん階段のあるような➡
Are you serious?
I thought it was common for them to
live in homes with spiral staircases.
家に住んでると思ってたぜ！
ああ それは ﾋｴﾗﾙｷｰで言うと
ﾄｯﾌﾟ ｵﾌﾞ ﾄｯﾌﾟの人たち｡
Ah, that's just for the
ones at the very top.
だいたいは こんなもんだよ！
Most manga authors' houses look like this.
(小西)ああ お疲れさま 天知君！
Ah, thank you for your hard
work, Amachi-kun.
Uho.
(天知)ｳﾎ…！
ああ そこ
ｳﾝｺあるから気をつけて｡
Ah, there's poop over there,
so watch your step.
坂田さん これ 作家の天知君｡
Sakata-san. This is the manga
author, Amachi-kun.
天知君 今日は この坂田さんと
３人で打ち合わせすることに➡
Amachi-kun, today's meeting will be
between the three of us, including Sakata-san.
なったからね！
ｳﾎ…！
Uho.
(小西)あのね 坂田さん
基本 ｺﾞﾘﾗだけど➡
Well, Sakata-san. He's basically
a gorilla, but not a real gorilla.
ｺﾞﾘﾗじゃないから｡
いや ｺﾞﾘﾗだろ｡
No, he's a real gorilla.
(小西)ﾏﾝｶﾞ家なんて みんな
だいたい こんな感じだからね｡
Most manga authors are like this.
Basically, they're all gorillas.
だいたい 基本 ｺﾞﾘﾗだから｡
でも 『ｷﾞｮｷﾞｮのｽﾃｷな冒険』の
原木先生は ﾊﾝｻﾑだし➡
But Haraki-sensei of "Gyo Gyo's Wonderful Adventure"
is handsome and doesn't grow old.
[Note: Gyo Gyo's is a parody of Jojo's Bizarre Adventure by Toshiyuki Araki. Hirohiko is known for his appearance not changing for nearly 20 years.]
歳とらねえじゃねえかよ｡
(小西)あの人はｺﾞﾘﾗじゃないけど➡
He's not a gorilla, but an immortal fairy.
永遠の時を生きる妖精さんだから｡
まぁ いいや！ とりあえず
お前ら そっち座れ！
Whatever. Anyway, why don't
you guys sit down over there?
(小西)ああ そこ
ｳﾝｺあるから気をつけて！
Ah, there's poop over there,
so watch your step.
じゃ 今日は ｵﾚが みっちり➡
Well, today I'll teach you
about the basics.
基礎から 叩き込んでやっから｡
(天知)ｳﾎｯ！
Uho.
まぁ ｵﾒｴらのﾏﾝｶﾞは
だいたい読ませてもらった｡
Well, I've read most of your manga.
おもしろくねえから
飛ばし飛ばしだが➡
It wasn't interesting, so I just skipped a lot
of it, but the storyline is something like this.
だいたいの流れは
こんな感じだろ？
東京という 架空の街を舞台に➡
In a fictional city called Tokyo,
the smart and refined man,
軽妙洒脱な男 ｷﾞﾝﾀさんが➡
Ginta-san, with his happy friends
Patsuan and Gurako, run wild!
愉快な仲間 ぱっつぁん
ｸﾞﾗ子たちと一緒に大暴れ！
[Gintaman]
...That's the basic concept.
基本ｺﾝｾﾌﾟﾄは こうだな｡
で さっそく言わせてもらうと➡
Then I'll tell you what.
まずね 根本的なところ
主人公が かなり ﾔﾊﾞｲよね！
First, basically, the design for
the main character is crap.
はい これ ｷﾞﾝﾀさん！
ほ～ら 見た目 地味すぎ！
Here, this is Ginta-san.
See, his appearance is too plain.
(小西)そうかな？
一応 ｷﾞﾝﾀって名前にちなんで➡
Really? His name is Ginta, so
we made his hair silver...
[Note: Gin means silver in Japanese.]
髪の毛 銀髪にしたり…｡
(天知)ｳﾎｯ！
Uho.
はい お前らは ﾊﾞｶですか？
Fine. Are you guys stupid or something?
基本画面が 白黒のﾏﾝｶﾞで
色で特徴を出して どうすんだ！
The manga is basically black and white.
Why did you use color
to make it stand out?!
(小西)あぁ そうか
あ そういや そうだな｡
Ah, I see. Ah, that's right.
Uho...
ｳﾎｰ！
あぁっ 落ち込まないで 天知君！
Ah! Don't get so disappointed,
Amachi-kun!
いいか 例えば このｷﾞﾝﾀさんを
ｼﾙｴｯﾄにしてみよう｡
Listen. For example, let's make
this Ginta-san a silhouette!
ほ～ら見ろ これ
何の特徴もねえだろ？
See?! Look at this. There're no special
characteristics at all, are there?
Kids won't remember
a character like this!
こういうｷｬﾗは
子供は 覚えてくれません！
If he's not a character you can
identify by his silhouette,
ｼﾙｴｯﾄだけで
見分けがつくくらいじゃねえと➡
you can't survive in manga for boys.
少年ﾏﾝｶﾞは
やっていけねえんだよ！
例えば これ
誰だか わかるかい？
For example... Can you tell who this is?
Ah! Yes! Yes! Zoffy of One Park!
[Note: Parody of Luffy from One Piece.]
(小西)あ！ はいはい！
『ﾜﾝﾊﾟｰｸ』の ｿﾞﾌｨｰ！
じゃあ これは？
(小西)あっ 『ﾍﾟｽﾉｰﾄ』の ﾙｰｸ！
What about this?
Ah! It's Luke of Peth Note!
[Note: Parody of Ryuk from Death Note.]
じゃ 次は？
(小西)『ﾌﾟﾘｰﾁ』の十護｡
The next?
Jugo of Pleach! That's right!
[Note: Parody of Ichigo from Bleach.]
あっ 本当だ
みんな ｼﾙｴｯﾄだけで わかる！
They're all identifiable from
just their silhouettes!
はい じゃあ これは？
(小西)『ﾄﾞﾗｺﾞﾝﾎﾞｰｽﾞ』の悟忠！
And how about this?
Gochu of Dragon Bozu.
[Parody of Goku from Dragon Ball.]
ﾌﾞｯﾌﾞｰ 違います｡
Bu bu. That's wrong.
えぇ？ 悟忠だよな
あれ絶対 悟忠だよ！
What?! That's Gochu! That's
definitely Gochu!
Uho!
ｳﾎｯ ｳﾎｯ ｳﾎﾎﾎ｡ ｳﾎｯ ｳﾎｯﾎ！
あ～ 天知君 落ち着いて！
Ah, Amachi-kun, calm down!
正解は…｡
The answer is...
...Ginta-san.
ｷﾞﾝﾀさんです｡ 正確に言うと
来週からの ｷﾞﾝﾀさんです｡
To be exact, it's the Ginta-san
from next week on.
Well, if the main character has these attributes,
I think it'll be all right. Yeah...
まぁ これくらい特徴あれば
まず大丈夫だと思うよ？
うん 天知 来週から これな｡
Amachi, use this starting next week.
(天知)ｳ… ｳﾎ…｡
(小西)いや…｡
U-Uho.
No, wait... Well... That looks
just like... Dragon Bozu's...
ちょ…
あの それ 完全に 『ﾄﾞﾗｺﾞﾝﾎﾞｰｽﾞ』の…｡
は？ ﾄﾞﾗｺﾞﾝ… なに？
わけわからんこと 言うな｡
Huh? Dragon...what? Stop saying
things that I can't understand.
あ… いや え？
Ah, no.... Huh? You just said you've been
reading JUMP for twenty years, right?
ｱﾝﾀ ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣20年読んでるって
言ってなかったっけ？
Anyway, the Gintaman's serialization
is already in its fifth week,
だいたい 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』の連載は
もう５週目入っちゃってるから➡
そんな いきなり
主人公の ﾋﾞｼﾞｭｱﾙ変えても…｡
so we can't suddenly change the
visual look of the main character
to something completely
different now, anyway.
つぅか ほとんど別人だし｡
You know, you can say his perm failed.
あれだろ？ ﾊﾟｰﾏ
失敗したことにすれば いいだろ｡
あと 爆発したとか ﾎﾞﾊﾞｰﾝって｡
ｳﾎｯ！
Or he had a perm explosion... Boom!
Uho!
なに そのｱｲﾃﾞｨｱいただきみたいな
顔してんの！
Why does it look like you're
saying, "I'll take that idea!"
We already had something
ridiculous like that before!
その前に とんでもないもんを
いただいちゃってるんだよ！
は～い じゃあ 主人公ときたら
次は 敵！
All right, we finished the main character,
so next we'll talk about the enemy!
(小西)おい！
話 勝手に進めてるし！
Hey! You're pursuing this
subject all by yourself!
いいか 主人公を立たせるには
強力なﾗｲﾊﾞﾙが 不可欠だ｡
Listen! In order for the main character
to stand out, a strong rival is needed.
そう 『ﾜﾝﾊﾟｰｸ』の秩父会しかり｡
Right... Like One Park's Chichibukai.
Or Belt's "Bakazuki."
[Note: Parody of Shichibukia and The Seven Warlords of the sea from One Piece and Bankai from Bleach and the Akatsuki from Naruto.]
[CHICHIBUKAI]
『ﾍﾞﾙﾄ』の ﾊﾞｶﾂﾞｷしかり｡
[BAKAZUKI]
The main character beats his strongest
enemy, so it makes him cool.
いかにもっていう
強力な敵を倒すから➡
主人公が かっこよく見える｡
そして その強力な敵が
仲間になったりするから➡
And sometimes a strong enemy
winds up becoming a friend,
so he becomes more exciting.
燃えるわけだよ｡
う～ん｡
Hmm...
So, Gintaman's rival character is...
で 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』での ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗは…｡
ｺｲﾂか？ っつうか 何だ これ？
This guy? Who's this, anyway?!
(小西)新宿署のﾃﾞｶ 泥方さんだね｡
It's a detective from the Shinjuku
police station, Dorokata-san.
[Note: Parody of Hijikata.]
時に ｷﾞﾝﾀさんを
追いつめ➡
Sometimes he hunts down Ginta-san
and sometimes he helps him.
[DOROKATA]
時に ｷﾞﾝﾀさんに
協力する｡
It's a character that screams, "closest
rival" but is really a "friend."
好敵手と書いて
友と読む ｷｬﾗだよ｡
ｶｰｯ ﾍﾟｯ!! だから➡
I already told you that it's too plain! Can
you identify him by his silhouette?
地味だっつってんだろうが！
ｼﾙｴｯﾄで見分けがつくか？
これ あん!?
何回も言わせんじゃねえよ｡
Don't make me repeat the same
thing so many times.
Are you guys stupid or something?
ﾊﾞｶか ﾃﾒｴらは！
見ろ これ!!
Look at these. In JUMP, these are the
silhouettes of the rival characters.
｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣における
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙたちの ｼﾙｴｯﾄを｡
ほ～ら 一人も
かぶってねえだろうが！
See, no one looks the same.
って いや もう ｱﾝﾀ
完全に知ってるよね｡
So you do know all about it, right?
You know about Dragon Bozu, right?
『ﾄﾞﾗｺﾞﾝﾎﾞｰｽﾞ』 知ってるよね｡
つぅか 知らないからね｡
Well, it's not my fault if the top people
come complaining to us.
偉い人から
ﾊﾁｬﾒﾁｬが押し寄せてきても！
Shut up and die.
ｼｬﾗｰｯﾌﾟ そしてDie！
I'm sure the top people will be able
to handle it, so don't worry.
きっと上のほうで
なんとかしてくれっから 大丈夫｡
Nothing to worry about.
へっちゃらだから！
(小西)本当かよ!?
I doubt it!
More importantly, look
carefully, right here.
そんなことより ほら
ちゃんとこっち見て｡
はい これ 誰か わかるか？
(小西)えっと ﾋﾟｯｸﾙさん｡
Well, do you recognize who this is?
Um... Pickle-san.
[Note: Parody of Piccolo from Dragon Ball.]
じゃあ これは？
(小西)
このﾂﾙｯとした頭は 天津丼さん｡
Then, how about this?
That shiny head belongs
to Tenshindon-san.
[Note: Parody of Tien Shinhan from Dragon Ball.]
はい じゃあ これ｡
(小西)あっ ﾊﾞｼﾞｰﾀ！
And this?
Oh, Bajita.
[Note: Parody of Vegeta from Dragon Ball.]
ﾌﾞｯﾌﾞｰ 違います｡
Bu bu. That's wrong.
What! Don't tell me... This
time, the rival character...!
(小西)あっ まさか
今度は ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗを!?
正解は… ｷﾞﾝﾀさんです｡
The answer is...
...it's Ginta-san.
To be precise, it's Ginta-san after
he turns into a Super Yasain.
[Note: Parody of Super Saiyan from Dragon Ball.]
正確に言うと ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人になった
ｷﾞﾝﾀさんです｡
(小西)なんでだよ～!!
なんで また ｷﾞﾝﾀさん!?
Why?! Why is Ginta-san here again?!
Why are you asking such
tricky questions?!
なに ひっかけ問題 作ってんの!?
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗの やりとりは➡
What was the point of talking
about rival characters?!
なんだったんだよ！
つぅか なんで ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人に➡
And why did he turn into
a Super Yasain?!
なってんだよ！ なんで
着実に強くなっていってんだよ！
Why is he steadily getting stronger?!
Uho
[Ginta-san.]
なに ひっかけ問題
乗り越えてんだ!?
Why did you answer such
a tricky question?!
Stop smiling! This isn't a quiz!
嬉しそうな顔すんじゃねえ！
ｸｲｽﾞやってんじゃねえんだよ！
So, this rival character appears as an enemy
at first, but ends up being a friend.
で このﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗは
最初は 敵として出てくるが➡
最終的には 仲間になるのが
少年ﾏﾝｶﾞの醍醐味になっている｡
That's the real thrill of a boy's manga.
Then what's the meaning
of this discussion?!
(小西)さっきのやりとりは
なんだったんだよ！
何の意味があったんだよ！
まぁ こういう感じだな｡
Well, it's something like this: He
fights with his rival and wins.
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙと戦って 勝つ｡
いつの間にか 仲間に｡
Then they become friends
without knowing it.
新たに ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙ出現 戦って 勝つ｡
新たな仲間が できる｡
And a new rival appears, and
he fights and wins again.
And he makes a new friend.
Repeating this and dragging it on
is the standard JUMP formula.
これを延々と繰り返していくのが
ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟｼｽﾃﾑというやつだ｡
(小西)おい～！ １人だけ
入ってねえぞ！
Hey! One person is missing! Namcha?!
Is that Namcha?
[Note: Parody of Yamcha from Dragon Ball.]
ﾅﾑﾁｬか!? ﾅﾑﾁｬのことかぁ!?
Well, that's what the
rival part is all about.
まぁ だいたい
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙ編は こんなところかな｡
Hey! Let him in! Let Namcha
join in the JUMP formula!
(小西)おい～！ 入れてやれよ
ﾅﾑﾁｬも➡
ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟｼｽﾃﾑに 入れてやってくれよ!!
次は そうだな
ｺﾒﾃﾞｨ的な部分に触れようか！
The next thing is... Let's talk
about the comedy part.
Namcha!
ﾅﾑﾁｬ～!!
Well, as far as appearances go, "Gintaman"
is more like a comedy manga...
まぁ読んだところ
この 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』というﾏﾝｶﾞ➡
ｺﾒﾃﾞｨ色の強いﾏﾝｶﾞみてぇだが➡
知ってのとおり ｷﾞｬｸﾞというのは➡
...but as you know, a gag is created
by a funny man and a straight man.
ﾎﾞｹとﾂｯｺﾐというのがあって
はじめて成立する｡
There're some gags where there's only a funny
man and no straight man at all, but...
なかには ひたすらﾎﾞｹて
一切つっこまないｷﾞｬｸﾞも➡
あることには あるが…｡
If that's the case, the reader can be
the straight man while he reads.
その場合 読者が読みながら
つっこんでいる｡
笑いが あるところには
必ず ﾂｯｺﾐが存在する｡
Wherever there's laughter,
there's a straight man.
ﾂｯｺﾐの重要性が ｵﾒｴらにも
わかっただろう？
Now you guys understand how important
it is to have a straight man, don't you?
Uhoho!
ｳﾎｯﾎ！
ただ｡
However...
『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』においては このﾂｯｺﾐ➡
...in Gintaman's case, I can see that
this straight man went slightly too far.
少々やりすぎな面が うかがえる｡
これを 見てほしい｡
Please take a look at this.
(小西)うん？
Uho?
Huh?
[REWIND]
はい！
なんでなんだよ！
Watch.
[PLAY]
Why?! Why is Ginta-san here again?!
なんでまた ｷﾞﾝﾀさん!?
なにひっかけ問題 作ってんの!?
Why are you asking such
tricky questions?!
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗの やりとりは
なんだったんだよ！
What was the point of talking
about rival characters?!
つぅか なんで
ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人になってんだよ！
And why did he turn into
a Super Yasain?!
Why is he steadily getting stronger?!
なんで 着実に
強くなっていってんだよ！
はい 見てもらったとおり
このﾂｯｺﾐは明らかにやりすぎです｡
All right. As you can see, this straight
man is obviously overdoing it.
This isn't manga. It's what I said earlier!
これ ﾏﾝｶﾞじゃなくて
さっきの ｵﾚのやりとりだろうが！
A straight man's role is to explain the funny
man's joke so that people understand, but...
ﾂｯｺﾐというのは
ﾎﾞｹのおかしな点を➡
わかりやすく
教えてやる役目を担っていますが｡
はい｡
なんでだよ なんでまたｷﾞﾝﾀさん？
Watch.
Why?!
Why is Ginta-san here again?!
なに ひっかけ問題つくってんの？
Why are you asking such
tricky questions?!
What was the point of talking
about rival characters?!
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗの
やりとりはなんだったんだよ！
つぅか なんで
ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人になってんだよ！
And why did he turn into
a Super Yasain?!
なんで 着実に
強くなっていってんだよ！
Why is he steadily getting stronger?!
こうもおかしな点を
丁寧に拾われると 逆にさめます｡
If he nitpicks about every little thing
like this, people will get bored.
Watch.
はい！
なんでだよ なんでまたｷﾞﾝﾀさん？
["WHY" 0 times]
Why?! Why is Ginta-san here again?!
["WHY" 1 time]
["WHY" 2 times]
なに ひっかけ問題つくってんの？
Why are you asking such
tricky questions?!
What was the point of talking
about rival characters?!
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗの
やりとりはなんだったんだよ！
And why did he turn into
a Super Yasain?!
つぅか なんで
ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人になってんだよ！
["WHY" 3 times]
なんで 着実に
強くなっていってんだよ！
Why is he steadily getting stronger?!
["WHY" 4 times]
See? You said "WHY?"
four times in one cut.
ほら～ １ｶｯﾄで
｢なんで｣って４回言ってるからね｡
やめてぇ～ なんか
恥ずかしいからやめてくれない？
Stop! I'm so embarrassed,
so please stop it!
ﾂｯｺﾐなんかは かえって適当な
ほうが効果的だったりします｡
When the straight man is played in a
subtle manner, it's far more effective.
It encourages the reader to actually think about
the joke and the straight man's explanation.
というのは もともと
｢おかしい｣ ｢変だ｣という➡
理解不能な
部分からくるものであり➡
この状態は
どこかに曖昧な部分を含まねば➡
It helps suck the reader in. But when
you try to explain everything...
成立し得ないもので➡
これを１から10まで
説明すると はい｡
Watch.
(小西)
なんでだよ なんでまたｷﾞﾝﾀさん？
Why?! Why is Ginta-san here again?!
なに ひっかけ問題つくってんの？
Why are you asking such
tricky questions?!
What was the point of talking
about rival characters?!
ﾗｲﾊﾞﾙｷｬﾗの
やりとりはなんだったんだよ！
And why did he turn into
a Super Yasain?!
つぅか なんで
ｽｰﾊﾟｰﾔｻｲ人になってんだよ！
なんで 着実に
強くなっていってんだよ！
Why is he steadily getting stronger?!
You've obviously lost your
effectiveness as a straight man
このように 明らかに
ﾂｯｺﾐとしての役目を失い➡
むしろ 不快なものとして
受け取られかね…｡
and have become plain
annoying instead...
やめろよ～っ わかったよ！
Stop! Fine! Kill me! Everything
will be all right if I die!
殺せよ！
ｵﾚが死ねばいいんだろうが！
要するに ﾂｯｺﾐは➡
In other words, the straight man's
job isn't to just explain something.
ただ説明すればいいと
いうものでは ねえということだ｡
Aren't you just pointing out my faults?
(小西)もうなんか普通に
ｵﾚへのﾀﾞﾒ出しになってない？
まっ そんなところで
ちょっと ｵﾚの知り合いに➡
Anyway, that's about it.
I have someone who is the top straight man
in Edo, so you'd better learn from him.
江戸いちばんの
ﾂｯｺﾐ使いがいるから➡
いろいろ
教えてもらえ｡ 紹介するわ｡
Let me introduce him to you.
ｷﾞﾝﾀさんです｡
This is Ginta-san.
Dondake!
[Note: "Dondake" is a popular catch phrase used by gay people in Japan. Literally means "WTF?!" Similar to American gay people who snap their fingers and say "Oh no you didn't!"]
(新八)どんだけ～！
It's something like that.
I invented that phrase recently.
といった具合だ｡
最近 考案したﾂｯｺﾐでな➡
ほぼ すべてのﾎﾞｹを処理できる｡
どんだけ～！
It can cover almost all
funny-man situations.
Dondake!
If you keep using that word most
of the time, it'll be all right.
だいたい全編 このﾂｯｺﾐを
貫いときゃ 大丈夫だ！
(小西)どんなｺﾒﾃﾞｨだよ それっ！
違う 違う！
What kind of comedy is that?!
No, no.
どんだけ～！
(小西)ど どんだけ～！
Dondake!
D-Dondake!
もう１回！
どんだけ～！
One more time.
Dondake!
ﾜﾝ ﾓｱ ｾｲ！
どんだけ～！
Say it once more!
Dondake!
(小西)どんだけ～！
ｴﾌﾞﾘﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ ｾｲ！
Everybody say it!
Dondake!
どんだけ～！
(小西)どんだけ～！
Dondake!
(MC)さぁ 今年の流行語大賞は？
And this year's top buzzword is...
"Dondake!"
｢どんだけ～｣に決定！
(歓声)
Everybody, "Dondake!"
(小西)ｴﾌﾞﾘﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ どんだけ～！
[LIVE]
[This year's buzzword award!]
[Shonen JUMP Editorial Department
Kohei Konishi]
Here we have Kohei Konishi-san
who created "Dondake!"
(記者)｢どんだけ～｣の
生みの親と言われる➡
『週刊少年ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ』編集部➡
He is from the weekly Shonen
JUMP editorial department.
小西 恒平さんに
きていただきました｡
どうですか 今のお気持は？
Please tell us how you feel right now.
Well, it's not like I wanted to
launch a new catchy trend...
いや～ ﾎﾞｸとしては
流行の発信基地になるとか➡
そういう考えは 全然なくて➡
I just worked hard and it
came about naturally.
ただ がむしゃらに仕事してきて➡
So I don't know what to say.
そこから自然に生まれたもの
なんで なんとも言えませんが｡
ただ
若い人にひと言 言いたいよね｡
But...I have just one thing
to say to young people.
自分のおもしろいと
思うものを とことん考えて➡
If you have something that you really think
is fun, think about it and pursue it.
とことん追求しろって｡
(小西)結局 それが成功をつかむ➡
After all, that's the shortcut
to success, I think.
いちばんの近道なんじゃないかな｡
[Meet a deadline! By Konishi.]
Uho.
なんやかんやで やっぱり
楽しんで仕事してるﾔﾂには➡
Whatever... No one can overcome
someone who loves his work.
誰も敵わないよね ｱﾊﾊﾊｯ…｡
(吉沢)ﾁｯ 負けたぜ…｡
(編集長)ﾌﾝｯ！
Tsk... I lost...
Humph!
早く ここまであがってこい 小西｡
I look forward to seeing
you at this new level.
Konishi.
Lastly, I'd like to say one word to all my friends
who taught me something important.
最後に
ﾎﾞｸに大切なことを教えてくれた➡
友人たちに ひと言 言いたい｡
Dondake!
(小西)どんだけ～ ｱﾊﾊｯ…！
It's still so boring...
[Note: On JUMP cover, "Gintaman
becomes TV Anime!']
相変わらず おもしろくねえなぁ｡
早く終わんねえかなぁ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』｡
I hope Gintaman ends soon.
[This episode celebrates the 40th anniversary
of Weekly Shonen JUMP]
Gintaman. Gintaman.
[Gintaman]
[Note: This song is a parody of the Dragon
Ball Z anime opening song.]
Gin Gin Gin Gin Gin.
Gintaman.
[Original story by: Hideaki Amachi]
In the night, he keeps running in the city.
Where is he going?
[Special Thanks to Weekly Shonen
Jump Kohei Konishi]
That's not important.
Half spirited Ginta-san.
Domestic Violence!
Look at yourself in the mirror, Gurako-chan!!
Patsuan!!
Gintaman. Gintaman.
[Main theme "Dondake! Gintaman"
Song by Ko-saku]
Gin Gin Gin Gin Gin.
Gintaman!
Sparking!!
どんだけ～！
まぁ 落ち着けよ 新八｡
Dondake!
Hey, calm down, Shinpachi.
このｱﾆﾒ 『銀魂』も なんとか
３年目を迎えることができたが➡
The GinTama anime is barely
entering its third year.
原作のｽﾄｯｸが
数えるほどしかねえ！
However, there's only a few original
manga episodes left.
だから 来週から
１か月 ｵﾘｼﾞﾅﾙｱﾆﾒ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』を➡
Therefore, the staff intends to
broadcast the original anime
"Gintaman" for one month
starting next week.
放送しようっていう
ｽﾀｯﾌの考えだ｡
Dondake!
どんだけ～！
(神楽)うるさいｱﾙ 新八！
Shut up, Shinpachi.
Today, how many times
did you say "Dondake"?
お前 今日どんだけ
どんだけ～ 言うｱﾙか！
Nowadays, saying "Dondake" too many
times is really embarrassing.
今どき どんだけ～
連発って ﾑｯﾁｬ恥ずかしいｱﾙ！
うっ…｡
察してやれ 神楽｡
Consider his feelings, Kagura.
今日の原作がｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟに
のったの いつか知ってっか？
Do you know when today's story
ran as manga in JUMP?
去年の６月だぞ ６月！
It was in June of last year.
Back then, it was a big hit.
そんときゃ ﾎｯﾄなﾈﾀだったんだ｡
新八だって 今
どんだけ～を連発するのは➡
Even Shinpachi feels really ashamed
when repeating "Dondake!" now.
すんげぇ～ 恥ずかしいんだ｡
ﾒｯﾁｬ恥ずかしいんだ！
He's really embarrassed.
うっ…｡
そうか 新八は➡
I see. Shinpachi feels very embarrassed
right now. He's super embarrassed.
今 とっても恥ずかしいｱﾙか！
ごっさ 恥ずかしいｱﾙか！
う… どんだけ～！
って言うか～！
"Dondake!" I won't say it!
I'll never say it again!
もう言うか～！
ﾎﾞｸだって恥ずかしいんですよ！
I'm embarrassed! But I have no choice!
でも 仕方ないじゃないですか！
今日の台本見たら➡
I looked at today's script, and
found only "Dondake!"
どんだけ～
しか書いてないじゃないですか！
Furthermore, there's no way we can broadcast
something as ridiculous as "Gintaman"!
つぅか それよりもあれ 『ｷﾞﾝﾀﾏﾝ』！
あんな
危なっかしいもん放送できるか！
We'll be called in by the
top people again!
また偉い人に
呼び出しくらうだろうが！
I look ugly, so I don't like it, either.
私もなんか
ﾌﾞｻｲｸになってるから ｲﾔｱﾙ!
仕方ねえなぁ
せっかく名案だと思ったのによ！
Tsk, it can't be helped then.
I thought it was a great idea, though.
わかったよ
普通にやりゃいいんだろ？
All right, we just have to do
it the regular way, right?
I don't know what "regular" even means.
もう何が普通か
わからないですけどね！
Then, let's get started again! Here we go.
じゃ 仕切り
直していくか！ はい せ～の！
The GinTama Anime starts its third year!
(３人)ｱﾆﾒ 『銀魂』 ３年目ｽﾀｰﾄ！
Huh? Is it over?
えっ 終わり？
[Preview]
It's a familiar uniform... and a familiar
stance... But his face is...
What are you doing in a place
like this, Hijikata-kun?
You're...
["Rules Are Made to be Broken"]
[His name is Kamotaro Ito. A feeling
of chaos in the Shinsengumi...]
["The Shinsengumi Crisis Arc"
will start in the next episode!]